A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts and Culture Unit (MAC), Office Files of Elizabeth Richards FA505
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts and Culture Unit (MAC), Office Files of Elizabeth Richards
1997-2009
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Richards, Elizabeth Theobald
FA505
2.66 Cubic Feet 7 letter size boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the files Elizabeth "Betsy" Richards created when she worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC). The files document her managing the Foundation's grant portfolio on Indigenous Knowledge and Expressive Culture. The collection is comprised of one series of subject files.
The collection documents the Ford Foundation's program activities for expanding the field of Native American arts and culture through increased philanthropy and capacity building, support to different Native American arts and culture organizations in a variety of genres and areas, intellectual property rights, and tribal education. Several files show a global consideration of Indigenous peoples in addition to supporting Native American tribes, Alaska Natives, and Native Hawaiians.
Common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, memos, notes, drafts, reports, articles, proposals, grant action records, and publications. There are also a few digital media items in the collection.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of one series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1997-2009
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in three accessions between 2019 and 2021 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2019:187, 2020:028, and 2021:135.
Ford Foundation; North America; Culture; Indigenous art; Indigenous art -- North America; Indigenous peoples; Intellectual property; Museums; Native Americans; Theater
- Subject files, 1997-2009; 1; 2.66 Cubic Feet 7 letter size boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Elizabeth "Betsy" Richards created and maintained when she worked as a Program officer in the Ford Foundation's Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC). Richards' subject files document her activities managing the Foundation's grant portfolio on Indigenous Knowledge and Expressive Culture.
  The series provides insight into the development, objectives, activities, and products of the Ford Foundation's programming for Native American arts and culture in the 2000s. Richards' Program Officer Memo drafts and notes show her suggestion to name the grant portfolio Indigenous Knowledge and Expressive Culture to better represent concepts used by Indigenous Peoples. These documents also outline the initiatives of the portfolio – Strengthening the Field of Native American Arts and Culture and Advancing the Dialogue on Native American Arts in Society. Other records show the Foundation's activities for gathering and analyzing data related to past grants for Native American issues.
  Files show the work of internal Ford Foundation groups and projects like the Committee on Indigenous Peoples (CIP) and IllumiNation. CIP examined the Foundation's grantmaking for Indigenous Peoples throughout the world and IllumiNation sought to expand philanthropy for Native American arts and culture.
  Other files show the grant support the Ford Foundation gave to various Native American arts and culture organizations in theater, museums, radio, music, and basketmaking. Grantees were also interested in intellectual property rights and tribal education for Native American youth. Many of the files are named after grantees of Richards' portfolio.
  There are also some files which document the Ford Foundation's broader work in arts and culture, especially its activities for marginalized communities like African Americans and Arab Americans.
  - Program Related Investments (PRI) information, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Reserves Request memo, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Theatre Communications Group (TGC), 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Program Officer Memo – Schedule, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Program Officer Memo – Drafts, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Program Office Memo – Notes, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Program Officer Memo – Research, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lannan Foundation, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Native Nations Institute (NNI), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Large Grantmaking to Native Americans – Sarah Hicks and Miriam Jorgensen, 2005 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Intellectual Property Rights: Challenges and Opportunities for the Ford Foundation – Joe Karaganis, 2004 November (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Grant inheritance from Ken Wilson, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Native American Arts and Culture Fund – Funders' Briefing, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - IllumiNation – First Convening, October 2006 at Ford Foundation (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - IllumiNation PowerPoint, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Open for research. Digital access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Emerging Writers of Color, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Native American issues grants from 1991-2001, 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Native American grantees 1990-2001 maps, circa 2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Grants and Budget System (GBS) Easy Access reference guides, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Grantmakers in the Arts (GIA) 2003 Conference (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ford Foundation Committee on Indigenous People (CIP), 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - International Training Center of Indigenous Peoples (ITCIP) - Giving Voice - Giving Hope, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ford Foundation Committee on Indigenous People (CIP), 2006 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ford Foundation Committee on Indigenous Peoples (CIP) - Revised policy on international fora, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Convenings, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Convenings - Imagine the Future: The Arts in a Changing America, May 21, 2004, at Ford Foundation (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Alison Bernstein - Talking points, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Articles, 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Canada Council for the Arts - Ford Foundation Committee on Indigenous Peoples (CIP) reception, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Tohono O'odham Community Action (TOCA), 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The Public Theater Native Theater Festival, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - The Public Theater Native Theater Festival - Tales of an Urban Indian play, 2006-2009 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - The Public Theater Native Theater Festival, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
  - Pono Kaulike - Native Hawaiian Traditional Knowledge and Intellectual Property Project, 2004-2007 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - South Western Association for Indian Arts (SWAIA), 2007 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - PA'I Foundation, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Penumbra Theatre Company (PTC), 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Potlatch Fund, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Native Americans in Philanthropy (NAP), 2007 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Native American Public Telecommunications (NAPT) - Native American Radio Theatre, 2002-2007 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Native Radio Theater PROMOS, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Native Radio Theater - Super Indian - The Series, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Native Radio Theater - Various programs, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - National Association of Tribal Historic Preservation Officers (NATHPO) - Bambi Kraus, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - New Orleans Museum of Art (NOMA), 2007 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - New York Foundation for the Arts (NYFA) - Jock Soto documentary, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Mid-America Arts Alliance (MAAA), 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art (MOCA), 2006 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Native Arts and Cultures Foundation (NACF), 2006-2009 (Box 4, Folder 47-49)
  - Native Arts and Cultures Foundation (NACF) - Hou Band of native Hawaiian Indians of the Blood of Hawaii complaint, 2003-2009 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Native Arts and Cultures Foundation (NACF), 2004-2007 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Suzan Shown Harjo - Individual grant, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Hawai'i Community College, 2007-2008 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Honor The Earth, 2003-2007 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
  - Institute of American Indian Arts (IAIA), 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Lalakea Foundation, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Longhouse Education and Cultural Center, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Maine Indian Basketmakers Alliance (MIBA), 2005-2007 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - IllumiNation, 1997-2008 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - American Composers Forum (ACF), 2003-2008 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Eiteljorg Museum of American Indians and Western Art, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Eiteljorg Museum of American Indians and Western Art - RARE (Reaching out with Artists in Residence at the Eiteljorg) PowerPoint presentation, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Path Breakers: 10 Years of the Eiteljorg Fellowship for Native American Fine Art, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Evergreen State College - Longhouse Education and Cultural Center, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - First Peoples Fund, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Smithsonian Institution National Museum of the American Indian (NMAI), 2005-2009 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Smithsonian Institution National Museum of the American Indian (NMAI) - Modern and Contemporary Native Art Initiative, 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - American Indian Community House (AICH), 2006 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Alaska Native Heritage Center (ANHC), 2006-2008 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Arab American National Museum (AANM), 2005-2008 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Atlatl National Native Arts Network, 2005-2007 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - New England Foundation for the Arts (NEFA) - Native Arts, 2006-2008 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Seventh Generation Fund for Indian Development (SGF), 2005-2007 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - American Association of Museums (AAM), 2007 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Smithsonian Institution National Museum of African American History and Culture (NMAAHC), 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - American Indian Artists (AMERINDA), 2003-2008 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - American Indian Institute (AAI), 2007-2008 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Basketweavers' Convenings - Longhouse Education and Cultural Center, 2006-2007 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - California Indian Basketweavers Association (CIBA), 2006 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Creators' Rights Alliance, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Denver Art Museum (DAM), 2006-2007 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts (DIA), 2007-2008 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Detroit Symphony Orchestra (DSO), 2007-2008 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Detroit Symphony Orchestra (DSO), 2009 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Eiteljorg Museum of American Indians and Western Art correspondence, 2008 March 11 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - European Foundation Centre (EFC) Annual General Assembly and Conference, May 2008, Istanbul, Turkey - Delegates list (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - American Composers Forum (ACF) First Nations Composer Initiative (FNCI), 2006 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Fund for Folk Culture - Envisioning Convergence: Cultural Conservation, Environmental Stewardship, and Sustainable Livelihoods, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Grantmakers in the Arts (GIA), 2006-2008 (Box 7, Folder 88)